<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A loving invitation (to repentance, and amendment of life) unto all the inhabitants of the island Barbados Before the Lords sore judgements come upon them, which is seen to be nigh, and which they cannot escape, except fruits meet for repentance, and amendment of life be brought forth. With somthing more particularly to the heads, and owners, of the several plantations. By a friend to the whole creation, called Richard Pinder.</title>
            <author>Pinder, Richard, d. 1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232175</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897845</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897845</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137389</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90710)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137389)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2536:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A loving invitation (to repentance, and amendment of life) unto all the inhabitants of the island Barbados Before the Lords sore judgements come upon them, which is seen to be nigh, and which they cannot escape, except fruits meet for repentance, and amendment of life be brought forth. With somthing more particularly to the heads, and owners, of the several plantations. By a friend to the whole creation, called Richard Pinder.</title>
                  <author>Pinder, Richard, d. 1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Robert Wilson, in Martins Le Grand, near Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bermuda Islands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137389:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137389:1"/>
            <p>A LOVING INVITATION (To Repentance, and Amendment of life) Unto all the INHABITANTS OF THE Iſland Barbados. BEFORE THE Lords ſore Judgements come upon them, which is ſeen to be Nigh, and which they cannot eſcape, except Fruits meet for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and Amendment of Life be brought forth. WITH Somthing more particularly to the Heads, and Owners, of the ſeveral PLANTATIONS.</p>
            <p>By a Friend to the whole Creation, called <hi>Richard Pinder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> in
<hi>Martins Le Grand,</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:137389:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:137389:2"/>
            <head>A loving Invitation (to Repentance, and Amendment of life) unto all the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Iſland <hi>Barbados.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>OH <hi>Barbados!</hi> Liſten oh Iſland! for the Lord hath a ſore and great Controverſie with thee, becauſe of the Lewdneſs, and Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations that are found in thee, which the Righteous ſoul hateth, and which the Lord is bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with; that though he be mercifull, and full of pity, and bear long; yet nevertheleſs, the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed cannot go unpuniſhed, nor eſcape his ſore and great Judgement: For ſo he hath determined, that the wicked ſhall bear the weight of their own wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And oh Iſland, conſider the wickedneſs that is committed in thee is great; that it is become even as a Mountain before the Lord of Hoſts; that Vile, and Contemptible, thou art in his ſight, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath repleniſhed thee, and filled thee with earthly Fruit, and Subſtance; and yet thou rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt againſt him, as though thou couldeſt bring forth Fruit of thy ſelf. O conſider, and call to mind thy former dayes, wherein thou waſt little in thine own eyes, and in the eyes of all that knew thee. (Mark) O all ye Inhabitants of this Iſland! many of you are Full, and Rich, and the ſins of
<hi>Sodom</hi> are found among you; fulneſs of Bread, and abundance of Idleneſs. Oh how is the Creatures
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137389:3"/>of God abuſed, and deſtroyed among you, in ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying your ungodly luſts? Do you think the Lord takes no notice of all your wickedneſs, and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian-like Practices? Are you not bad Examples unto all about you; both to the Heathen, and them that have the Name of Chriſtians? Do your think you can eſcape the Lords Hand? Will all your Riches, and Greatneſs in the Earth, defend you from it? Oh no: his hand is Mighty, and his ſtroke will be Grievous; and aſſuredly it will fall heavy upon the Heads of the Wicked; and eſpecially upon them whom he hath ſuffered long, as he hath done thee, oh Iſland: yet provoketh him to diſpleaſure, thou dayly doth, by the Sins which dayly abound in thee, and are brought forth by the Tillers, and Manurers of thee: That though, oh Iſtand, thou yeildſt unto them Fruit, and Subſtance in abundance, yet againſt him (who cauſeth the pleaſant ſhowers to come upon thee) they rebell. Oh bring thou forth Thorns and Thiſtles for their ſake, that they may read their Figure, and ſee how unfruitfull they are unto him, who repleniſheth thee, who is the God of the whole Earth, whom all ought to ſerve, and obey, and not their ungodly luſts, which oh Iſland, deſtroyes thy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe; that I ſay bring thou forth, and be thou over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with unfruitfull Weeds, that thy Inhabiters may read their Figure, and ſee how they cumber the ground, and how they are become as an unfruitfull Wilderneſs unto him, who hath been gracious unto them, in cauſing thee to yeild encreaſe in abundance; but with it their hearts are made fat, and corrupted before the Lord, whom they ought to ſerve, and obey, with their whole heart, who is diſpleaſed with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:137389:3"/>their ungodly luſts; and is coming forth of his Holy Habitation, to puniſh, and reprove, becauſe of them; that they oh Iſland, may know that they have rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt him, and diſpleaſed him, in letting their hearts be carried away, and exalted with the Riches which thou brings forth, and yeilds unto them. For why, oh Iſland, ſhould thy Inhabiters diſhonour the God of the whole Earth, through being puffed up, and exalted by the abundance of Fruit which thou brings forth? For doth not he, who is the God of the whole Earth, who cauſes the former, and the latter Rain to come upon thee, (that thou mayeſt bring forth fruit) create all things for his own glory and honour, to be uſed in his fear, and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and not to ſpend in ſatisfying the luſt? that why, oh Iſland, ſhould not thy Inhabiters know, that he, who cauſeth Rain to come on thee, will above all be Honoured, in bleſſing them with an everlaſting bleſſing, that walks humbly before him; and in pouring forth his judgements, in the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his wrath, upon thoſe which obey him not, but obey unrighteouſneſs, which oh Iſland thy Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters do: For which cauſe the wrath of God is neer to be revealed from Heaven in flames of fire, that vengeance may be taken upon all ungodly men; and indeed, to deal plainly with thee oh Iſland, thou art fill'd with them, as I may take the witneſs of God in every Mans Conſcience, (who knows thee in the State thou now art in) to bear record, that plainly thy State and Condition is ſeen to be miſerable; for the wickedneſs that abounds in thee is great, and the weight of it hath lain for ſometime upon my Spirit: which thing I am now moved to publiſh unto thee;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137389:4"/>and I dare not but do it. For verily the Lord hath let me ſee that his wrath is waxed hot, and nigh to break forth in thee, if repentance be not ſpeedily ſought, by turning from the evill, and chuſing that which is good. And I clearly ſeeing, oh yee the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this Iſland, that there is no other way, whereby you can eſcape the heavy hand of God, but by turning away from the evill of your wayes, and coming into amendment of life. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am conſtrained, by the compaſſion of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, which is to all your Souls, to lay ſome things before you, as an Information unto you. But this firſt I would have you to underſtand, that while you are in that State (the greateſt part of you are now in) I cannot ſpeake peace unto you. For if I ſhould, then I ſhould be like thoſe abhominable Deceivers, which are among you, who prophecy ſmooth things unto you for their own ends; that they may live in the ſame exceſs of rioting with you; but little of them (the covetous hireling Prieſts I mean) I need ſay unto you: For you know that they are a company of men, not at all like any, whom God ever ſent into his work, to convert Souls unto himſelf; but more like a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of men that never heard of Chriſt, nor hath any regard unto peoples Souls, as their fruits makes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and by the fruit every Tree is know. As Chriſt ſaid, by their fruits the falſe Prophets ſhould be known. And this oh <hi>Barbados</hi> may be a ſufficient proof, that thy Teachers are not according to the mind of God, their diſorderly walking; but believe them not, though they cry peace, peace unto thee; while the evill abounds in thee, as it doth at this day.</p>
            <p>Unto all you, who are the Maſters, and Owners of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137389:4"/>the ſeverall Plantations, am I moved to write, and to lay ſome things before you to be conſidered of in the fear of the Lord. You, many of you, hath many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you as Slaves, and Bond-Men: Therefore conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Places, and be not high minded, but fear; provoke not your Servants through cruell uſage, for that the Lord hates; they are of the ſame Blood, and Mould, you are of; and you muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your actions unto the Lord, as well as they, &amp; with him there is no reſpect of perſons; for his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is True, and Juſt; and the Sentence which proceedeth out of his Mouth is right, according to that of God in all Conſciences; ſo liſten, and take a word of advice, now while the Day and Time is, that you may learn Wiſdom, and make your Peace with God. But know firſt, that before you can come into peace, with God, you muſt let his witneſs ſearch your hearts; and truly it will find much in the hearts of many of you, which is to be condemned and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, before you can come into peace with God; for he is pure, and hates the Garment ſpotted with the fleſh; and he turns his mighty hand againſt all Iniquity, where his pure witneſs finds it. And oh ye Heads of the ſeverall Plantations of this Iſland, You are generally a lofty, and high Minded People, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Luſts and Pleaſures of this preſent Evill World; that many of you are become without ſenſe or feeling of any thing of God; that the God of this world hath ſo far prevailed, that your eyes are become eves wholly blind; that truly the darkneſs, even the thick darkneſs, which lies over you, may eaſily be felt by any whoſe hearts God hath opened unto himſelf; and into this great, and thick darkneſs, and benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:137389:5"/>State you have run your ſelves, by giving way, and following your ungodly luſts, which is conceived in your Earthly Minds, which run forth in Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, after the earth; which many of you have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to be your God, and ſo have denyed the living God, who gives you life, and being; and all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that conſider; you whoſe hearts are thus bowed down to the Earth, and Earthly things, your State and Condition is miſerable; for the God of Heaven and Earth, will require an account of you, for all his Creatures (which he hath given you) which you ſpend in ſatisfying your Luſts, and able to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him you will not be; and your mouths will be ſtopped by his Witneſs, in your Conſciences, which now in this the Day wherein the long ſuffering of God is upon you, you reject, and do deſpite unto. And thus you reject the day of your Viſitation: And ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily it is nigh at an end with many of you, that the day of deſtruction haſtens greatly, and it ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take every one that is proud, and lifted up: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider, while time is, for it is precious. And truly it will be your burden one day, that you have ſpent ſo much precious time, in rioting, feaſting, and drunkenneſs; through which you deſtroy Gods Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; when, as alas, many of your Servants, both white People, and Negroes, are like to periſh, and be deſtroyed for want of the Creatures: and thus you burden the Creation, by being Subject unto your own Luſts: For conſider, if the Wiſdom of God did lead you, it would bring you to uſe his Creatures to his Glory; and then it would be your care, Oh ye Heads, and Owners of the ſeverall Plantations, that none of your Servants, or Slaves did periſh, or ſuffer, for want
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:137389:5"/>of the Creatures; and alſo it would be your care, if the Wiſdom of God you lived in, which is the Wiſdom of the Creation, that none of your Servants, nor any under you ſhould abuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the Creatures of God through drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And then if theſe things be your care, God would bleſſe you; but ſo long as you are bad exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples your ſelves unto your Servants, you ſtrengthen them in their wicked deboiſt wayes; and thus you become guilty before the Lord, both of their, and your own wickedneſs; then let amendment of life be brought forth, that youmay become good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to all under you, in patience, in moderation, and ſobriety, in your Words and Actions; and that will be the way, whereby you may eſcape Gods ſore Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and be freed from his wrath to come. For you being good examples both in word and behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, this will anſwer the witneſs of God in all you are over: and this will reach more deeply into their hearts, and conſtrain more obedience then all your cruell uſage (in whipping them,) For conſider, if you whip them for drunkenneſs, and ſuch like things, and you your ſelves be guilty of the ſame, this greatly hardens their hearts againſt you, and provokes them to curſe you behind your backs. And thus you cauſe the Name of God to be blaſphemed, through your diſorderly walking; and being bad examples unto them, whom in the Wiſdom of God you ſhould rule over, and keep ſubject unto you; as I ſaid, being bad examples your ſelves, this looſes your Authority, which otherwiſe you might have, if you were kept in the Fear and Wiſdom of God your ſelves: For
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:137389:6"/>that would keep you humble before Lord; that though you had much of the earth, yet you would not be exalted, nor lifted up in your ſelves, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed (Oh ye Heads of the ſeverall Plantations) is your greateſt ſin. For in that which is ſo exalted, and lifted up, by having much of the earth, is all iniquity wrought, and all deceiveableneſs of unrighteouſneſs: &amp; thus the earth is made a curſe unto you, as it is unto all whoſe minds are not redeemed out of it. And none comes to know, and have their minds redeemed out of the earth, but they that come to know him reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them, who is from heaven, (to wit) the Son of of God, the ſecond
<hi>Adam,</hi> who redeems, and leads out of the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> State, who is of the earth, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And ſo all whoſe mindes are in the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, they are in the unredeemed State, drove into the earth from God, where he ruleth that filleth the earth with ſpoile, and violence, the old Serpent, the Devill, and Satan, by whoſe power all are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, that knows not ſomething of God in them, to keep their minds out of the earth. For all naturally in the fall and tranſgreſſion, are inclined unto the earth, and its Riches and Glory; and ſo it keeps them from ſeeking after the Riches, and Glory, which is Eternall. And truly this is the State of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who have much of the earth, as you have, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this Iſland: and truly the hearts of many of you are greatly corrupted through the abuſe of it, and your conſciences greatly burdened, through cheating, and couſening one another about it, that your wickedneſs is grown to an exceeding great height; yea, as I ſaid, it is become even as a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137389:6"/>before the Lord; that long you cannot ſtand, except repentance be ſought, and amendment of life be brought forth. For the Lord hath ſpared long, and born much; for your ſins exceeds both in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and number, the ſins of many people; even as far as you exceed many people in earthly riches, and honour; that though you become famous in the worlds eye; yet you do not appear ſo in Gods eye; for he loaths your curſed practiſes, and will aſſuredly puniſh you for them; that though you account it now pleaſure to riot in the day time, yet your pleaſure ſhall be turned into ſorrow; and all your laughing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing into mourning, &amp; howling; that it were good for you to conſider betime, upon what ground you ſtand, that if peradventure God might grant you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to amendment of life; ſo that you might his ſore and great puniſhment eſcape, which no way you can eſcape, but by ſpeedy repentance: Therefore take yet a word of advice, oh ye great, and rich ones in the earth, If you intend that God ſhall bleſs you, then put away far from you all high-mindedneſs, cruelty, and hard-heartedneſs, which at this day abounds among you in your ſeverall Plantations. And you the Heads and Owners of them are deeply guilty of theſe things. Now to remove theſe, and ſuch like things from your ſeverall Plantations, this would be your way, Put ſuch men in place, to be Overſeers of your Servants, as fear God, and hate drunkenneſs, and ſwearing, and all ſuch things, that they may rule over them in moderation, and not in Tyranny, and hard-hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and this will be the way to beget love in your Servants unto you, and one to another; and ſo love
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:137389:7"/>being begotten in your Servants unto you, and one unto another, this will ſtop abundance of cruelty, and wickedneſs, which doth abound among you; and let not your Overſeers (I warn you all) rule in ſuch Tyranny over your Negroes; for if you do, you will bring blood upon you, and the cry of their blood ſhall enter into the eares of the Lord of Sabbath, (for he made them, &amp; giveth them life) and it ſhall cauſe his wrath to break forth upon you, and if you thus provoke the Lord, by letting them, who are your Slaves, be wrongfully entreated, and unmercifully uſed, it is much, if the Lord bring them not, as a Rod upon you: however let the Lord be clear, and me clear in his ſight, in that I warn you of it now, while you have time to mend it; and take heed you abuſe not the long-ſuffering of God, but let it lead you to Repentance, &amp; amendment of life; for if the long-ſuffering of God comes once to an end, that his Spirit leave ſtriving with you, know then, That your State is miſerable; for no other way can, either high or low, rich or poor, bond or free, come to be reconciled in peace with God, and eſcape his judgements, but by giving regard to be led by his Spirit, which ſtriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with them, in reproving of them for their ſin, which ſeparateth them from God: (Now Mark) that which reproves you for ſin, is of another nature then ſin; for it is the gift of God, which is come upon you, and all men, to give life unto all that receive it, and walk as it leadeth. For it leadeth all that believes in it, and obeyes it, from death, and all dead works unto life; and ſo redeemeth from the earth; where the bondage is, into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:137389:7"/>liberty of the Sons of God: which Liberty is not to the Luſts, but to the Soule, which the Luſts wars againſt; And from whence comes wars and fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? Are they not from the Luſts? and whence comes all pride, and arrogancy? comes it not from that part, which keeps the Soul in death? So conſider, you who are exalted, and lifted up in pride; and whoſe life ſtandeth in periſhing things, your Soules are not quickned unto God; for you reject, and hate the Light, an appearance of the ſecond
<hi>Adam,</hi> who is the quickning Spirit; who is the bread of God which never decayeth, which all that eateth, hath life in them, and lives for ever; and none elſe have life eternall abiding in them, but they who live by this bread. For alas, they are degenerated from God by tranſgreſſion; they feed, and are nouriſhed up in the Luſts of Ignorance, which alienates their minds from the life of Chriſt, and keeps them ſtrangers to it, in the envious and murderous Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. And no murderer hath eternall life abiding in them, but is condemned with <hi>Cain;</hi> of whoſe antiquity all murderers, and envious men are. So read your ſtock, and off-ſpring, you that are offering up Prayers for a Sacrifice, and yet have ſlain the witneſs of Truth in you; that it lies ſlain in the ſtreets of the ſpiritual
<hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> where the Lord of Life was ever Crucified. And you that are ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and deriders of others, <hi>Iſhmael</hi> is the root from whence you ſpring, and your ground is curſed; for your, hearts are ſet to do wickedneſs: And you that are ſcoffers, your tongues are ſet on fire on Hell; that ſo long as they are not bridled, your Religion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:137389:8"/>is vain, and your prayers not heard with God, nor your Sacrifices accepted. For they are not by Faith, (ſo long as you live in the ſcoffing nature) for you are like a wave of the Sea, (that is your Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure) foaming out of your own ſhame, and ſending forth the bitter waters, as Envy, Wrath, Hatred, and Malice; and theſe all ſpring from the corrupt Fountain, which corrupts the Earth, and defiles the the place where God ſhould dwell; (to wit) the heart and conſcience; that ſo the ſtrong man keeps the houſe in peace, and perſwades you all is well; and that Chriſt hath taken away your ſins, and that his Righteouſneſs is imputed to you in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight of God; and perſwades you, that God looks upon you in Chriſt, and not as you are of your ſelves: and thus feeds you with vain hopes; when as alas, you neither know Chriſt, nor his Righteouſneſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to you; but are in that nature, which is againſt his gift, which is come upon you to juſtification of life. Mark, the gift which juſtifies life, condemns all dead works, and all diſobedience; for which ſake, the wrath of God comes upon all men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and through the obedience and Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſs of Chriſt, the gift it comes upon all men. So you that are ſpeaking of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, being imputed unto you; and you in diſobedience to his gift in your conſciences; you are they that ſet up another faith then the Apoſtles did, who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed the faith of
<hi>Abraham,</hi> which was imputed unto him for righteouſneſs; by which faith he obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the voyce of God; but you that are ſpeaking of Chriſts Righteouſneſs imputed to you, and obeys
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137389:8"/>your luſts, and vile affections; you are them upon whom the Righteouſneſs of God is to be revealed in flames of fire, becauſe you hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs. That I ſay, that which may be known of God is manifeſt in you, and God hath ſhewed it unto you, that he hath enlightned you; and he doth not deſire the death of a ſinner, but rather all ſhould come to his gift (which through the obedience of Chriſt, is perfectly come upon them) and live; for the gift of God is life eternal, but the wages of ſin is death. All thoſe who are in the pleaſure of ſin, they are forth of the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of faith, and ſo forth of the Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs; for by faith <hi>Moſes</hi> denyed the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſin, and ſo was counted worthy to ſuffer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction among the people of God; who ever ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſuch as live in hard-heartedneſs, and in the luſts of Ignorance, and according to the will of the fleſh; For he that is born after the fleſh, perſecutes him that is born after the Spirit. So all by the light, which you are enlightned withall: Read your ſelves, and ſearch your own hearts, and take warning betime; for verily, if you live according to the fleſh, you muſt die; but if you, through the Spirit, mortifie the deeds of the fleſh, then you ſhall live. And thus I have ſet before you, Death, and Life; and the way whereby you may come to repentance and amendment of life, and ſo come to the knowledg of the truth, and be ſaved; which is the whole deſire of my ſoul: that though you chuſe death, &amp; do live according to your own luſts; I ſhall be clear in the ſight of God, in that in faithfulneſs I have written, what he requires of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:137389:9"/>me; which otherwiſe I could not be clear of your blood. For verily, the Lord hath let me ſee, that he will not ſpare you long, except the evill of your doings you turn from. So take this as a warning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you all; both high and low, rich and poor, bond and free; though moſt it was upon me, to write unto the Heads, and Owners of the ſeveral Plantations; yet it may ſerve as a warning unto all the Inhabitants of this Iſland, or a ſore judgement nigh at hand, if Repentance be not ſpeedily ſought,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Barbados
<date>the 10<hi>th</hi> day of the 8<hi>th Month</hi>
1660.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>R. P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:137389:9"/>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:137389:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:137389:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
